Alan Davies ｜ ACDCs for Enterprises ｜ KERI Conference 2026
… and thank you all for being here. So,
I've been accused many times in the
past of oversimplifying. I can say
here and now that I never oversimplify.
However I do like to simplify
things and the world out there needs to
understand what KERI and ACDCs can
deliver to the world and we need to
find ways of simplifying our messages to
them to make sure that they get it.
I thank Thomas [Mayfield, red.] for his great
presentation explaining in high-level
terms what KERI is all about and then
diving into the lower level detail and
I'm going to a certain extent
follow that track.
Let's get going.
I want to start by talking about how
trust used to work.
It used to be
all about personal reputation. This
in the days when you wanted to carry out
some kind of transaction, buy something,
you would go along to the person who was
selling it or providing it. You would
talk to them, you would make a deal, you
shake hands and you would decide
whether you're trusting them or not. If
you trusted them, you would give them
their money. They would give you the
goods and off you went. And so trust
depended on physical presence.
All of the verifications that took place
were pretty well immediate and you
would decide do I really trust this
person? If so here's your
money. I'll take the goods now or
maybe later.
Fraud did exist. Of course there would
be people who would promise to do
something and then not deliver it but
the scale was limited to I guess the
person that they were they were doing
the deal with.
So that was in the distant past. Now
things have changed and in fact they
changed at least a couple of hundred
years ago when the ability to
communicate in different ways came
along.
But it they changed in a very big way
when global communications arrived
firstly with the telephone and then
Fax machines and of course now
the internet.
What the internet enabled us to be able
to do is execute transactions remotely
which is a great thing in many ways.
It enabled international commerce to
be able to scale up in so many
different ways and also allow regular
humans to participate in that
kind of commerce. We can go
online to Amazon, we can buy what we
want when we want and it turns up the
next day. It's very convenient.
In order to support that, when the
internet came along, it was a almost a
natural knee-jerk reaction to say, well,
if people are going to use online
systems, they need to authenticate to
be able to access it. And usernames and
passwords was the way that we did that.
So you log in, you get a session
token and the system that
you're talking to uses that token to
decide what you're allowed to do.
The end result so far has been rampant
online fraud and we've done what we can
to limit that. Mostly by trying to
detect fraud which is in my view a
losing battle. The fraudsters have so
many tools available to them to be able
to fool the general public into
thinking that they are someone
legitimate.
and detection is we're always going to
be losing that battle to try and detect
fraudulent activity.
This is my own
personal view of the distant future in
which everything that we do will be
signed. So, it's a signed intent
world
and I think the way we'll end up if you
think maybe four or five years in the
future
We will all have an agent on our
devices that does things for us.
You'll ask your agent AI agent to do
something. It'll be maybe move some
money from your checking account to your
savings account.
the AI agent on your device because it
knows you've authenticated with that
device biometrically. It'll wrap
that request in an ACDC,
sign it with your private key.
It'll just use your face ID or whatever
other biometric it's using to make sure
it really is you.
It may add additional signatures if
necessary. So if you're a child
using your device, it may be that
whatever you're asking your agent
to do requires your parents permission.
So, you may get an additional signature
added to that request.
That request may include relevant
credentials, your SEDI credential for
example, or who knows what other
entitlement credentials that
you may have.
That request will then get sent to some
kind of execution service. If it's your
bank, because you're moving money from
one account to another, then it'll be
your bank's online system.
It'll verify the trustability of that
request. It'll see where it came
from. It will see your signature. It
will see your maybe your parents
signature if you're a child. It will
do the usual KERI ACDC stuff.
Verify it hasn't been tampered with.
They it they know it's you and the bank
will then execute that request and make
a record of it. And
I don't think there will be a need to
have a username and password. You won't
need to login for this because basically
you've sent a signed sealed
request to your bank that they know it
came from you. They'll execute it.
They'll record it and that's the end of it.
I'm exaggerating here. I'm sure there
will be passwords, sessions tokens, and
2FA for all sorts of stuff, but in
the long term, they will be at least
less necessary. And in the example I
gave you, you can imagine a world where
everything you do is signed intent.
I think that this is going to be how we
reduce the rampant online fraud to ..,
there's always going to be fraud,
unfortunately, there always going
to be someone who will find a way of
fooling someone else into doing
something they shouldn't be doing.
But this is the long-term vision and
this is all going to be delivered,
in my view, with implementations of
KERI and ACDCs,
and everything that we've been talking
about today.
However, there's going to be a lot of disruption
to be able to enable all of that. I mean
the example I gave you about the bank
they need to rearchitect their systems
so that they are accepting
signed requests from their customers
that they identify through their
their online identity
that the customers own and that's
going to be a great world of course
everybody will be their own identity
provider which is how it should be if
you think about it. I'm the only
person who knows that I am me. And if I
control a digital identity that
asserts that, then I'm by far the best
person to be able to prove who I am.
And I don't like the idea of delegating
that to some
other federated identity provider.
However, they're not going to like it at
all. The federated identity
providers are having lots of information
from people every time they log in. So,
there's going to be a lot of resistance.
Information harvesters are going to
hate all of this because everything that
Sam [Smith, red.] tells us that we should be in
control of is not what they want us to
be in control of, sadly.
As I mentioned, all sorts of online
services will need to do a lot of
rearchitecting to implement that final
vision.
And this isn't going to happen in the
next 12 months.
There will be movement towards it but
In my view, we need to
do something sooner to start
getting KERI and ACDC adoption in a
small way and then move on. So this is
where we are now. We have rampant online
fraud.
Autonomous AI agents are doing more
and more stuff and working out how to do
things on their own.
Mostly because they think that they are
doing what we want them to do but not
necessarily.
The current way of recording what
happens is really online logging. So the
the bank will keep a record of what you
asked it to do moving money from one
account to another. But if someone
gets my password and asks my bank to do
something on behalf of me then as far as
the bank logging is concerned it was me
doing it which just is not real. So it
is it's just weak.
So what we really need is what I call
trustability.
And trustability is the ability to
be able to make a good trust decision
on any kind of action that you might be
Intending to make based on some
information that comes at you over the
internet. And it can be something as
simple as a news article.
Did this journalist really write this?
Do I trust this journalist? The trust
decision might be very weak. I'm just
going to develop my own opinion
about whatever is being written about
based on based on that journalist's
reputation. But
other things are much more important.
If I see a request from one of
my kids to send some money to a bank
account because he's in trouble, then I
need to be able to trust that is
really from my son. And I need to
make a trust decision. I might need to
make it quickly. So how do we
get trustability into the world of
online transactions?
And what we need of course is KERI and
ACDCs and we need .., I hate to say
"a little bit of KERI and ACDC" because we
need the whole thing but we
can't very quickly implement the
entire or reimplement the entire online
access infrastructure to support the
the long-term vision of how the whole
world of signed intent is going to
work.
And
where digital trust foundry is
starting, is saying that what we
need is something that we call execution
trust.
Immediately before making some kind of
Decision to execute some kind of
action based on information that's
coming to us remotely. And that might
be we're a supplier receiving a
purchase order. We might be an employer
being presented with someone's
academic credentials before we hire them
for a job. Before we make that
decision, then
we need a way to be able to make
a trust assessment of what's being
presented to us.
And
this is where I think that what the
world needs is to be able to start
slowly and to be able to implement
what we call execution trust into
existing systems and of course start
with high value high-risk transactions.
For example wire transfer fraud. It
is way too easy for bad actors to be
able to make changes to wire transfer
requests as they move from place to face
before they get to the bank
that's going to execute that wire
transfer.
Taking a wire transfer request, wrapping
it in an ACDC, getting it signed by
the owner of the originating
account
means that when the bank gets it, they
can verify it, make a trust decision and
execute it and then keep a
cryptographically verifiable record of
what they were asked to execute for
any time in the future.
So what we're talking about is inserting
a level of trustability into existing
applications at execution time, hence
the term execution trust.
And this can apply to any digital
artifact. Verifiable
credentials was really all about
academic and professional credentials
but ACDCs are really capable of
handling any kind of data content that
might be delivered from one trust domain
to another.
Even better in the short term, it makes
sense even with a single trust domain to
be able to take some kind of
action. Let's say, it's updating a
production system. We have an
update that we want to make to a
production system and we want to make
sure that it's fully authorized before
we execute it. And of course,
that update may have been
generated by AI. So it's kind of
important that a human gets involved in
that process. A workflow
application that's going to apply that
update to the production system could
take that description of that update
request, wrap it in an ACDC, send it to
the CIO to say, "We're about to
update your production systems with
this. Do you approve it?" He would sign
it, return it back. Then that
update application would say " Okay, I have
approval to go ahead with
with this update, apply the update, keep a
record" and that all happens within a
single trust domain. What you've
done there is applied a little bit of
KERI and ACDCs to a particular high
value use case to make sure that
in that particular example the update
was being made was fully authorized
by someone who is the appropriate
authorizer of that update.
The same thing applies
across trust domains where maybe a
business generates a legal document that
needs to be signed by the CEO before it
gets delivered to a partner for them to
execute. You can build that kind of
functionality into an existing
application that's already generating
these documents. You just say, "Well, we
already have the document. It's a PDF.
We're just going to wrap it in ACDC,
get it signed, and send it off. And then
whoever gets it, because they know how
to verify an ACDC, we'll run a
verification. They know that it was
signed by the CEO, they can act on it.
I think that's basically what I'm
talking about here. And of course,
multisig comes in very useful in
situations like this.
The application at execution time can
verify and either decide to reject it if
it's not happy with what it sees or
executed and keep a permanent record of
its trust decision and what it made that
trust decision based on.
The benefits of this approach
which is a little bit of KERI and
ACDCs injected into existing business
applications for high value
transactions.
There are so many business use cases
that this can apply to across all
industries.
I know from personal experience that if
I use my bank's online system to do a
wire transfer even though I'm logged
in, it'll get to a certain point where
it says " We're going to send you a
code to your mobile phone and want
you to type it in. So, two-factor
authentication to make sure that even
though I'm already logged in that it
really is me again, sort of really me.
This would replace those kinds
of weak two-factor authentication with
what we call a hard gate.
There will be no need to rearchitect
existing systems. If you take for
example the bank's wire transfer
request system, they already have that
ability in their system. It's part is
the functionality of their banking
system anyway. The additional step
would be just to make an API call to
a platform that knows how to wrap that
content into an ACDC, send it to an
authorized signer, and return the signed
ACDC back. Then that application just
makes another API call to verify it,
looks at the results, makes a trust
decision, either rejects or
continues. No need to completely
rearchitect existing systems.
This will drastically reduce online
fraud for high value business
transactions and it can be done really
very soon.
I like to talk about this as
getting used to KERI and ACDCs one
bite at a time. So you introduce
something like this to a high value
transaction that's already being
executed by business applications
Today and they see the immediate
benefits and then once businesses start
using this technology in this limited
constrained way then they will be able
to see how that the basic technology can
be applied in all sorts of other
situations. And this is how we get the
world starting to use KERI and ACDCs
without having to make huge changes.
And also this is another good reason
for businesses to get a vLEI of course.
Digital Trust Foundry is a platform that
enables businesses to do exactly what
I've described. It's multi-instance
multi-tenant platform that fully
implements KERI and ACDCs with our
witnesses and watchers network.
(let me see if I'm getting ahead of
myself here)
We've implemented what we call a
trustables API. So the business
application can say "I have some digital
content that I want to make trustable."
It makes a call to the API
specifying the AIDs of the signers or
the roles that need to approve whatever
the digital artifact is that's being
processed.
The end result is, it gets back an
ACDC that it can verify
and that's where we're
starting. We're saying that we
need to provide what we call
execution trust to existing applications
so that they can start using the
power of KERI and ACDCs now in a
small way but then to see understand
the value of it by practical experience.
We're looking for partners. Our
business model is "Yes, we will deliver
our a platform" for use by
businesses generally but also by
partners who have existing applications.
It might be workflow applications
that need stronger approval processes
for example. And they can work
with us to build execution trust
functionality into their applications
and deliver it to their customers. So in
this way we build a network of
businesses who are implementing the
power of ACDCs and KERI without
having to build the whole thing
themselves. They just make use of our
platform. So in some ways it's similar
to if you're a business wanting to
Manage your sales process, you can
either use spreadsheets and build
your own application to manage all of
your sales processes or you can go to
Salesforce and sign up for a CRM with
them. they provide the functionality all
of the low-level detail and you just
get the benefits.
We have a list of interactive
examples of our functionality that
you can go and play with and just
to give you some ideas of the sorts of
things that can be done with that.
There's about 30 different use cases in
different businesses. One of my
favorites is verifiable résumés in
which an individual who's collected
digital credentials or professional
credentials can actually take them
all and generate a verifiable resume
that has references to all of each of
those credentials. and they can provide
their digital verifiable resume to a
potential employer who can actually
click verify on that resume. It will go
to the issuers of each of those
credentials, verify them and then return
a trust report to the employer.
That's all I have to say for now.
Thank you very much for your time and if
you have any questions now is the
time.
– I got one question because of the term
that you coined "trustability."
I use that in a promotion on
LinkedIn and it got a red
dotted line under it. It doesn't exist
in my translation. So it got
trustworthiness.
I heard your
explanation of trustability but
could we use the word trustworthiness
as well in your…
Of course, yes.
The ability to be able to make a trust
decision on something is my definition
of trustability which may not be a real
word. But I think it should be.
We're making trust decisions all
of the while. But when I receive some
kind of digital information over the
internet that I want to make a trust
decision on then I have, at the moment,
only two choices. One's called blind
faith. Well, there's three actually.
Blind faith. The one is ignore it
completely. And the third is spend quite
a lot of time doing some kind of
verification manually to decide whether
this is genuine or not. If it's an
email coming over from me, I look to see
where it actually came from, for
example. If you can trust that.
About a week ago, my wife had a phone
call from the Bank of America saying
that they noticed that someone is trying to
initiate a wire transfer from our
checking account. They said we
we can help you fix this.
They sounded very genuine and
they said this is my name and if
you go to the Bank of America's website
go to a particular branch and you scroll
down you'll see a picture of me and
you'll see my phone number and if you
look that the phone that I'm calling
from is in fact that phone number. So
this is me. my wife said, "Mmm,
well, I'm going to call you back
anyway." And that was the
last we heard of them, except we called
back and spoke to somebody completely
different.
We could have
got caught out very easily. Because
lots of people assume that if it says
that phone number and they prove that
the real person
controls that phone number that's where
it came from. Thankfully, we have
Provenant who is solving that problem for
us using KERI and ACDCs but for now
we're in the world where we have to make
either blind faith, ignore it or
spend some time doing verification and
and that's how we get caught.
Implementing
execution-time trustability is
where we think things should start.
Thank you. Any other question?
If not, then thank you very much, Alan, for
your presentation.